Finding aid to the Elizabeth Warren Olmstead papers. CA.MS.01140
Smith College Archives
Elizabeth Warren Olmstead papers
1928-1982
Smith College Archives
Olmstead, Elizabeth Warren, 1907-1982
CA.MS.01140
0.50 linear feet (1 box)
Contains research note books, correspondence, academic publications, a master's thesis, and class notes by Elizabeth Warren Olmstead, class of 1931 and instructor in geology.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Elizabeth Warren Olmstead was born in 1907 in Buffalo, New York. She completed her education at Smith College, earning an A.B in 1931 and an A.M in 1933. She worked at Smith for the majority of her career in the Department of Geology and Geography as an assistant (1934-35), a teaching fellow (1935-37), an Instructor (1937-1944), and as an Assistant professor (1944-50). Olmstead was instrumental in setting up the first field station in geology for a women's college, the Black Hills and Bighorn Mountains Field Station, of which she was director 1936-1937. During her time at Smith, she won the Walker prize in Natural History, the Naval Ordinance Development Award, and the Office of Scientific Research and Development Certificate. She published several articles and books, including The Origins of the Appalachian Drainage. Olmstead left Smith in 1951 to work in Washington D.C. She died in Buffalo, New York, in 1982.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the student and professional papers of Elizabeth Warren Olmstead. These include notes from her class on Civil Defense in 1942 and her master's thesis, correspondence with other scholars and with publishers, a collection of her scientific articles, photos, and news clippings about her career. The collection also contains her research notebooks/travel journals from her time travelling on the Alaska Highway, about which she wrote a short paper.
Olmstead, Elizabeth Warren, 1907-1982; Olmstead, Elizabeth Warren, 1907-1982
- Miscellaneous, 1945-1982 (Box 960, Folder 1)
- Correspondence and memorabilia, 1928-1929 (Box 960, Folder 2)
- "The Alaska Highway", no date (Box 960, Folder 3)
- Correspondence- miscellaneous, 1951-1953 (Box 960, Folder 4)
- Correspondence- from Howard A. Meyerhoff, 1947-1956 (Box 960, Folder 5)
- Correspondence- from Howard A. Meyerhoff, 1954-1956 (Box 960, Folder 6)
- Alaska trip, 1946 (Box 960, Folder 7)
- Alaska trip, 1947 (Box 960, Folder 8)
- Alaska trip, 1948 (Box 960, Folder 9)
- Alaska trip, 1961 (Box 960, Folder 10)
- Civil Defense class notes, 1942 (Box 960, Folder 11)
- Publications, academic papers, 1931-1951 (Box 960, Folder 12)
- Classroom materials, 1950-1951 (Box 960, Folder 13)
- The Physiographic Problems of the Reading Prong, no date (Box 960, Folder 14)
- The Physiographic Problems of the Reading Prong- master's thesis, 1933 (Box 960, Folder 15)